Guide to the North Carolina Association of Women Attorneys Records, 1978-2011 RL.00933
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
North Carolina Association of Women Attorneys records
1978-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
North Carolina Association of Women Attorneys
RL.00933
17.6 Linear Feet 12,750 items
The North Carolina Association of Women Attorneys (NCAWA) was founded in 1978 to support women legal professionals and women's legal rights. Accession (2009-0209) (11.6 lin. ft.; 7100 items; dated 1978-2009) includes administrative and organizational records from the North Carolina Association of Women Attorneys. Materials include membership directories, conference binders, surveys and other research about women in the profession, videotapes from annual conferences, committee and task force files, meeting minutes, articles of incorporation, photographs from events, and other related materials. Accession (2011-1018) (1.0 lin. ft.; 1000 items; dated 1998-2011) includes additional administrative and organizational records from the NCAWA. Materials include newsletters, membership directories, conference notebooks, continuing legal education (CLE) presentations, photographs, correspondence, and periodicals about legal matters. Accession (2013-189) (6.0 lin. ft.; 4500 items; dated 1978-2009) includes newsletters, brochures, membership directories, conference materials, and photographs of past presidents. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The North Carolina Association of Women Attorneys Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2009 and 2011.
Historical note
The North Carolina Association of Women Attorneys was formed in 1978 and recently celebrated its 30th anniversary in 2008. The NCAWA remains an active organization committed to increasing effective participation by women in the judicial system, in public office, and within the legal profession; promoting the rights of women under the law; and promoting the welfare of women attorneys in North Carolina. It works towards these goals through newsletters, resolutions, committees, annual conferences, endorsements, retreats, and education through coursework and scholarships. More information about NCAWA activities is available on its website, www.ncawa.org.
Collection Overview
Accession (2009-0209) (11.6 lin. ft.; 7100 items; dated 1978-2009) includes administrative and organizational records from the entire history of the North Carolina Association of Women Attorneys. Materials include membership directories, conference binders, surveys and other research about women in the profession, videotapes from annual conferences, committee and task force files, meeting minutes, articles of incorporation, photographs from events, and other related materials.
Accession (2011-1018) (1.0 lin. ft.; 1000 items; dated 1998-2011) includes additional administrative and organizational records from the NCAWA. Materials include newsletters, membership directories, conference notebooks, continuing legal education (CLE) presentations, photographs, correspondence, and periodicals about legal matters.
Accession (2013-189) (6.0 lin. ft.; 4500 items; dated 1978-2009) includes newsletters, membership directories, conference materials, brochures, and photographs of past presidents.
North Carolina; Women lawyers -- North Carolina; Videotapes; North Carolina Association of Women Attorneys; North Carolina Association of Women Attorneys; Women judges -- North Carolina
- Accession (2009-0209), 1978-2009; 9 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Accession (2009-0209) (11.6 lin. ft.; 7100 items; dated 1978-2009) includes administrative and organizational records from the entire history of the North Carolina Association of Women Attorneys. Materials include membership directories, conference binders, surveys and other research about women in the profession, videotapes from annual conferences, committee and task force files, meeting minutes, articles of incorporation, photographs from events, and other related materials.
  - Annual conferences, 2000-2008 (18 folders) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous publications, 1983-2001 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - NCAWA Survey of North Carolina attorneys, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - National Association for Women Lawyers survey, 1996-1997 (Box 2)
  - NCAWA survey, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Wake Forest Women in Law survey, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Quality of Life survey, 2003 (Box 2)
  - North Carolina State Bar long range planning, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Other women advocacy groups, 1992-2001 (Box 2)
  - Common status of women in legal professions, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
  - Status of women in legal professions, 1993 (Box 2)
  - North Carolina Bar Association Board of Governors, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Task Force on the Quality of Legal Services, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with other bar groups, 1984-2003 (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Constitutional Equality Amendment organizing kit, late 1990s (Box 2)
  - Women's Employment Law Center, 1987-1995 (Box 2)
  - Career Support Committee: Court Conduct Handbook, 1996 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - National Conference of Women's Bar Associations, 1996-1998 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Cassette tape: Repetitive Motion Injuries (Box 2)
  - Foam boards with pictures of early North Carolina women attorneys (Box 2)
  - Foam boards with pictures of early North Carolina women attorneys (Box 3)
  - Videotapes from NCAWA 2001 Annual Conference
    - Analyzing Covenants Not to Compete (Box 3)
    - Child Abuse Homicides (Box 3)
    - Immigration Panel (Box 3)
    - Legislative Update (Box 3)
    - Family Law Panel (Box 3)
    - View from the Bench (Box 3)
    - Right to Die (Box 3)
    - Corporate Clients (Box 3)
    - Challenging Health and Disability Benefits (Box 3)
    - Lunch featuring Mary Easley (Box 3)
  - NCAWA Founding Mothers (videotape) (Box 3)
    A DVD use copy exists for this item.
  - Chief Justice's Commission on Professionalism, 2002 (videotape) (Box 3)
  - North Carolina Minority Lawyers, 2001 (videotape) (Box 3)
  - NCAWA Business files, 1979-1984 (Box 3)
    Includes meeting minutes, bylaws, resolutions, budgets, articles of incorporation, and other administrative materials.
  - NCAWA Business files, 1984-2002 (Box 4)
  - Annual meetings and annual conferences, 1980-1990 (Box 4)
  - Annual meetings and annual conferences, 1991, 1995-1998, 2008 (Box 5)
  - Newsletters, 1980-2007 (4 folders) (Box 5)
  - Articles of incorporation, 1979-1983 (Box 6)
  - Gwyneth B. Davis Awards, 1989-1996 (Box 6)
  - Bertha B Holt Award, 1998 (Box 6)
  - Katharine Everett and VIP letters (Box 6)
  - North Carolina Bar Foundation women attorneys survey, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Commission on the Status of Women in the Legal Profession, 1993 (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - NCAWA's first year, 1978-1979 (Box 6)
  - Pay equity/comparable worth, 2004 (Box 6)
  - Status of Women publications, 1990s-2000s (Box 6)
  - NCAWA brochures (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Articles on women in the profession, 1980s-1990s (Box 6)
  - Electronic files and digital photographs (Box 6)
  - Membership directories, 1983-1998 (Box 6)
  - Membership directories, 2000-2008 (Box 7)
  - Photographs, 1986, unlabelled, and 2001 Conference (Box 7)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 7)
  - Photographs, 1988-2002 (Box 7)
  - Membership directories, 1983-2007 (8 folders) (Box 8)
  - Membership directories, 2007-2009 (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Annual conferences, 1996-1997 (2 folders) (Box 9)
- Accession (2011-1018), 1998-2011; 2 boxes
  Accession (2011-1018) (1.2 lin. ft.; 1000 items; dated 1998-2011) includes additional administrative and organizational records from the NCAWA. Materials include NCAWA newsletters, membership directories, conference notebooks, continuing legal education (CLE) presentations and discs, photographs, correspondence, and non-NCAWA periodicals about legal matters.
  - NCAWA newsletters, 1998-2000 (Box 10)
  - Periodicals, 1998-2010 (Box 10)
  - Annual conference materials, 1998 (Box 10)
  - Annual conference and miscellaneous materials, 1999 (Box 10)
  - Presentations, 1999 (Box 10)
  - Board notebook, 1999-2000 (Box 10)
  - Membership directories, 1999-2001 (Box 10)
  - Email correspondence, 1999-2010 (Box 10)
  - Last Chance CLE meeting materials, 2000 (Box 11)
  - Annual conference 2000 notebook (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Photographs, including February conference, 2000 (Box 11)
  - Retreat handouts, 2000 (Box 11)
  - CLE materials, 2005-2008 (Box 11)
  - NCAWA administrative materials, 2010-2011 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
- Accession (2013-0189), 1978-2009; 6 Linear Feet
  - Brochures, 1978 (Box 12)
  - Newsletters, 1981-1997 (Box 12)
  - Membership directories, 1983-1997 (Box 12)
  - Conference and appreciation, 1990 (Box 12)
  - Newsletters, 1988-2001 (Box 13)
  - Membership directories, 1997-2002 (Box 13)
  - Briefs, 1988-2001 (Box 13)
  - Judge's Journal, Spring 2000 (Box 13)
  - Brochures, 2002-2006 (Box 14)
  - Meetings, 2002 (Box 14)
  - Newsletter, 2003 (Box 14)
  - Self-Evident (newlsetter), 2005-2006 (Box 14)
  - Membership directories, 2002-2007 (Box 14)
  - Annual Conferences, 2006-2007 (Box 15)
  - Speaker letters, 2007 (Box 15)
  - Self Evident (newsletter) and brochures, 2007 (Box 15)
  - Membership directory, 2007-2008 (Box 15)
  - Conference, 2008 (Box 16)
  - Self Evident (newsletter) and brochures, 2008-2009 (Box 16)
  - Women of Wisdom celebration (Box 16)
  - Super Lawyers, 2008 (Box 16)
  - Awards and newspaper, 2009 (Box 16)
  - SCWLA and NCAWA Conference, 2009 (Box 16)
  - South Carolina Lawyers, 2009 (Box 17)
  - Civil Liberties Panel, 2009 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 2009 (Box 17)
  - Photographs of past presidents mounted on foam core, 1978-1994 (Box 18)
  - Photographs of past presidents mounted on foam core, 1994-2009 (Box 19)
  - Protecting NC's Shoreline (Box 20)
  - The Right to Die (Box 20)
  - GPI photos, 2007 (Box 20)
  - Martha Lawrence photos, 2008 (Box 20)
  - Oversized prints mounted on foam core depicting events (7), and "ERA: Where Do We Go From Here?" (Box 21)